<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/">
    <title>Maikel&#x27;s Blog</title>
    <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev" />
    <updated>2023-06-30T16:20:38+02:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Maikel</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://blog.maikel.dev</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Re-making www.maikel.dev in NextJS</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/re-making-wwwmaikeldev-in-nextjs-3.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/re-making-wwwmaikeldev-in-nextjs-3.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/51/nextjs.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="nextjs"/>
            <category term="learning"/>

        <updated>2023-06-30T16:20:38+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/51/nextjs.jpg" alt="" />
                    I’m learning NextJS by doing this course by my favourite Udemy tutor Maximilian. I’m going to divide this notes in sections same as the course and I’m going to use The simplest way to create an app is to use: npx create-next-app on the shell&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/51/nextjs.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p>I’m learning NextJS by doing <a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/nextjs-react-the-complete-guide">this course</a> by my favourite Udemy tutor Maximilian. </p>
<p>I’m going to divide this notes in sections same as the course and I’m going to use </p>
<h2 id="reasons-im-learning-it">Reasons I’m learning it</h2>
<ul>
<li>I want to design <a href="http://www.maikel.dev">www.maikel.dev</a> using it.</li>
<li>I want to refresh my knowledge of React since it has been a while since the last time I used it.</li>
<li>I want server-side rendering. I’ve seen how hideously slow SPA are on regularly powered computers. </li>
<li>I think React has far more future than Angular will ever have. </li>
<li>I ‘d like to do the Fedigrindr app using this too.</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="section-1-getting-started">Section 1: Getting started</h2>
<p>The simplest way to create an app is to use:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">npx create-next-app
</code></pre>
<p>on the shell console. </p>
<p>Shortcut to format document: Ctlr+Shift-i </p>
<p>A NextJS app seems to be a monolitic node app. </p>
<h3 id="why-not-choose-use-app-router">Why not choose use App Router?</h3>
<p>Because otherwise you create a different folder structure instead of the pages. </p>
<h2 id="section-2-react-refresher">Section 2: React Refresher</h2>
<p>ReactJS is used (same as Angular) to make pages reactive, seem instant. Also is all about components. Webs divided in smaller parts. </p>
<p>Also to create a basic skeleton of a React app. </p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">npx create-react-app
</code></pre>
<p>useState is a bit confusing. </p>
<p>Default router he uses:</p>
<pre><code class="language-bash">npm install --save react-router-dom@5
</code></pre>
<p>All the routing thing is boring since I know already what this all is. The only thing I neede to remember is that to pass properties you just pass them in props and every React object has props, e.g.:</p>
<h4 id="how-to-pass-properties-to-children">How to pass properties to children</h4>
<p>This can also be used to pass actions to the parents. </p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">// Some parent object
return (
    &lt;div&gt;
       &lt;ChildComponent someText=&quot;hello&quot; /&gt;
    &lt;div&gt;
)

// Some child component becomes:
function ChildComponent(props) { //Props need to be defined here otherwise can&#39;t be accessed. 

return (
   &lt;div&gt;
             &lt;h1&gt;{props.someText}&lt;/h1&gt;
     &lt;/div&gt;
     )
     
}
</code></pre>
<p>Don’t use normla links as they’ll be sent to the server which is redundant. Use “LInk” instead. </p>
<h4 id="render-a-list-of-jsx-elements">Render a list of JSX elements</h4>
<p>Note that each element of a list must have an (unique) ID added as the key prop.</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">&lt;h1&gt;Some list&lt;/h1&gt;
{DUMMY_DATA.map((single) =&gt; {
    return &lt;SomeChildComponent key={single.id} title={single.title}} /&gt;
})}
</code></pre>
<p>I need to remember change this Harvest task to NextJS-course I want to know exaclty how much time I’ve invested on this by the end of it. </p>
<h4 id="passing-content-to-another-component">Passing content to another component</h4>
<p>Use props.children</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">&lt;Example&gt;
&lt;div&gt;Something else&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/Example&gt;
</code></pre>
<p>Won’t render unless you pass props.children such as inside the Example component</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">return (
    &lt;div&gt;
        {props.children
    &lt;/div&gt;
)
</code></pre>
<p>Now whatever content was after the tag will be rendered too inside. That’s how you use Wrapper components (e.g.: Card). </p>
<h4 id="prevent-form-submission">Prevent form submission.</h4>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">
function submitHandler(event) { // You need event here
  event.preventDefault() // this is what actually prevents the form submission. 
    }

return (
&lt;form onSubmit={submitHandler}&gt; ....thje form content &lt;/form&gt;
)
</code></pre>
<h4 id="useref-to-use-the-details-of-a-form">UseRef to use the details of a form</h4>
<p>This is a ref prop that is used to get an element through a referent object, example. </p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">const titleInputRef = useRef();

function submit( ) {
    const enteredTitle = titleInputRef.current.value;
    someLogic(enteredTitle);
}

return (
&lt;form&gt;
        &lt;input ref={titleInputRef} /&gt;
&lt;/form&gt;
</code></pre>
<h4 id="reminder-how-to-send-http-request">Reminder, how to send HTTP request.</h4>
<p>Lots of packages, for this as usual. fetch() is the one built in. Example for POST request.</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">fetch(
    &#39;SOMEURL&#39;, 
    {
        method: &quot;POST&quot;,
        body: theData // Use JSON.stringify if needed
        headers: 
            {
            &#39;Content-Type&#39;: &#39;application/json
            }
    }
)
</code></pre>
<p>You could use Redis here for simplicity while testing</p>
<h4 id="using-usehistory-to-navigate">Using useHistory to navigate</h4>
<p>import it from the router. </p>
<p>then add </p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">const history = useHistory() // to the function 

//Imagine you have a fetch and want to trigger going somewhere

fetch(DOSOMETHING).then(
    history.replace(&#39;/somerelativepath&#39;);
)
</code></pre>
<h4 id="reminder-on-how-to-fetch-data">Reminder on how to fetch data</h4>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">fetch(&#39;someURL&#39;).then(response =&gt; {
        return response.json() // To convert it to JSON
    }).then(data =&gt; {
        doSomethingWith(data)
    });
</code></pre>
<p>Very probably other libraries don’t require to convert to manually to json as a step. </p>
<h4 id="using-usestate-for-loading">Using useState for loading</h4>
<p>Use state to change what’s visible on the screen while loading. Beware a fetch should have a useEffect to avoid running for all eternity. </p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">import {useState] from &quot;react&quot;

const [isLoading, setIsLoading] = useState(true);

// Then on the fetch function change it to call setIsLoading(false)
</code></pre>
<h4 id="using-useeffect-to-avoid-runnning-loops">Using useEffect to avoid runnning loops</h4>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">useEffect(() =&gt; {
            fetch(....)
        }, 
        [isLoading ] // Check the values on this array before executing the rest of the effect (the fetch), so in this case isLoading won&#39;t execute again. In this case isLoading shouldn&#39;t be there, and by being empty it&#39;ll only run once. 
        );
</code></pre>
<h4 id="react-context">React Context</h4>
<p>Common convention is to set up a Store folder. Alternatives to RC is Redux. </p>
<p>To create a context</p>
<pre><code>import {createContext, useState} from &quot;react&quot;;

const YourContext = createContext({
    users:  [ ],
    totalUsers: 0
});
// You also need a provider of that context
function YourContextProivider(props) {
// Here you can manage state same as in any other React component. 
    const [users, setUsers] = useState([ ]);
    
    const context = {
        users: users,
        titalUserS: users.length
    };
    
    return (
    &lt;YourContext.Provider value={context}&gt;
        {props.children}
    &lt;/YourContext.Provider&gt;
    )
</code></pre>
<p>I think it’s a singleton. You could save this as yourcontext-context.js in the store folder. 
The hook to access that one would be useContext</p>
<h4 id="how-to-use-usecontext">How to use useContext</h4>
<p>Well, same as useState, etc. </p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">import {UserContext} from  from &quot;whervever&quot;
const userContext = useContext(UserContext);
</code></pre>
<h2 id="section-3-pages--file-based-routing">Section 3: Pages &amp; File-based routing</h2>
<p>With file-based routing you simply create a file to route to it, inside the pages folder. If you want to create a folder the main one should be called index.js and all others will be subpages of that main one (whose name is the folder name).</p>
<p>For stuff that’s dinamic use folders and filenames with [id] or [client]</p>
<p>You could also use […slug] for pages that are of a blog (slug can be anything) or any Catch-all routes</p>
<h4 id="link-advantages">Link advantages</h4>
<p>By using link it prefetches anything from the link as soon as you hoover it. </p>
<h4 id="navigate-programatically">Navigate programatically</h4>
<p>Use router.push(‘theroute’) to go and be able to go back
Use router.replace(‘theroute’) to go but without being able to go back. </p>
<h4 id="custom-made-404-page">Custom made 404 page.</h4>
<p>Just make a 404.js page on the pages folder, give it whatever name you want and it is what will be shown.</p>
<p>I wonder how long until he explains componentisation so I can design a navigation menu. So far it seems as if every page is its own page. </p>
<h2 id="section-4-working-with-file-based-routing">Section 4: Working with file-based routing</h2>
<p>If you hae two pages in the same folder and one of them is [eventId] and the other is […slug] the first one will only be picked up as far as the user types the URL with just 1 varaialble, more than one will pick up the second page.</p>
<p>Create a foldr called components to store all the bits and pieces normal of Angular/React. You can call it whatever you want but that way won’t interfere with file-based pages. </p>
<p>To use eventId on the example about</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">const router = useRouter();
const eventId = router.query.eventId;
</code></pre>
<h4 id="wrapping-it-all-in-a-layout-with-a-header-and-footer">Wrapping it all in a Layout with a header and footer.</h4>
<p>Modify _app.js to be wrapped in a Layout wrapper component that has props.children on it. </p>
<p>I’m not exactly getting what a Fragment is. Ok I get it now thanks to <a href="https://react.dev/reference/react/Fragment">this</a></p>
<h2 id="section-5-page-pre-rendering-and-data-fetching">Section 5: Page Pre-Rendering and Data Fetching</h2>
<p>This is about SSR (server-side rendering) which is the key feature of NextJs. </p>
<p>NextJS have to types of pre-rendering, static generation and SSR on the fly. </p>
<h4 id="using-getstaticprops">Using getStaticProps()</h4>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">export async function getStaticProps(context) {}
</code></pre>
<p>The function must be written exactly like that and it’ll only execute on the server, never on the client, in fact it’ll be hidden from the client. There’s no window object. You can put DB code there for example. Or read from a filesystem file (useful for markdown or JSON for example). Use the FS module with async/await. </p>
<p><a href="https://nodejs.org/api/fs.html#promise-example">https://nodejs.org/api/fs.html#promise-example</a></p>
<p>It should return {props: whateverObject}</p>
<p>You can tell that function to work again on </p>
<p>You can say it with the props that you return, example</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">return {
        props: someObject, 
        revalidate: 10 // This would be th enumber of seconds to revalidate. 
        }
</code></pre>
<p>That’s incremental static regeneration. </p>
<h4 id="using-redirect">Using redirect.</h4>
<p>It’s another key inside getStaticProps where you coudl specify where to send the user in case the page didn’t load or the access to the DB didn’t work for any reason. </p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">return {
    redirect: &#39;/404-nodata
    }
</code></pre>
<h4 id="extracting-context-for-ssr">Extracting context for SSR.</h4>
<p>Instead of route.query.eventId (just recycling the example above, you’d use inside the getStaticProps this:</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">export async function getStaticProps(context) {
    const { params } = context;
    const eventId = params.eventId;
}
</code></pre>
<h4 id="using-getstaticpath">Using getStaticPath()</h4>
<p>Default behavior for dynamic pages is not to generate them, such as [eventId]</p>
<pre><code>export async function getStaticPaths() {
    return {
        paths: [
                {params: {eventId: &quot;1&quot;} }
                {params: {eventId: &quot;2&quot;} }
                {params: {eventId: &quot;3&quot;} }
        ],
        fallback: false
    }
}
</code></pre>
<h4 id="using-fallback-true">Using fallback: true</h4>
<p>Using fallback set to true stuff is generated before when first visited. Imagine one as before but with eventId:4. When using this you should put a loading page or something because nothing will be created no the first visit yet. </p>
<h4 id="not-found">Not found</h4>
<p>You can return {notFound: true} to send the user to a 404 Not found page in the absence of a product with the ID the user request for example. </p>
<h4 id="using-getserversideprops">Using getServerSideProps()</h4>
<p>This one is never statically pre-generated. You get access to params, req and res. Yoo cannot use it with getStaticProps because it wouldn’t make any sense. </p>
<pre><code>export async function getServerSideProps(context) {
const {params, req, res} = context
returns { props: thePropsObject} 
}
</code></pre>
<h4 id="whats-useswr-hook">What’s useSWR hook.</h4>
<p>Is one to use instead of useEffect() to get data from the client side. Just check the docs. </p>
<h2 id="section-6-project-time-page-pre-rendering--data-fetching">Section 6: Project Time: Page Pre-rendering &amp; Data Fetching</h2>
<p>If you set fallback to blocking on any of the functions of the previous section nothing will be generated until the generation of the data has finished. </p>
<h2 id="section-7-optimizing-nextjs-apps">Section 7: Optimizing NextJS Apps</h2>
<h4 id="the-head-component">THe head component.</h4>
<p>It is na import from NetxJS. It works to add stuff between Head tags. You could use it with the _app.js file to have a generic head for all pages. </p>
<p>If you use the same Head thing in different places with the same values, it takes the later one. </p>
<h4 id="the-_documentjs-file">The _document.js file</h4>
<p>I don’t think you’ll ever need this one but if you do check direclty <a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/nextjs-react-the-complete-guide/learn/lecture/25145892#overview">this</a> video. It is useful if you want to change the HTML document itself. </p>
<h4 id="optmising-images">Optmising images</h4>
<p>This is interesting. Using the Image component NextJS will optimise on the fly the image. Width and Height are mandatory when using this one. </p>
<h2 id="section-8-adding-backend-code-with-api-routes-fullstack-react">Section 8: Adding Backend Code with API Routes (Fullstack React)</h2>
<p>The code inside “api” won’t ever go to the client. </p>
<h4 id="you-must-use-the-api-folder">You must use the API folder</h4>
<p>NextJS requires that if you use an API it has the folder named “api”. 
It’s very similar to vanilla express but also uses the pages file-based format. So if you want a users api endpoint you just create a users.js file inside “api” folder and inside, similar as express:</p>
<pre><code class="language-js">function handler(req, res) {
    res.status(200
        .json({status: &quot;ok&quot;})
}
</code></pre>
<h4 id="communication-front-end-backend">Communication front-end backend</h4>
<p>If you’re going to use getStaticProps from the frontend then you shouldn’t use fetch since it’s all in your project. Instead you should DRY and make the code you have in your API a function that can be accessed from getStaticProps()</p>
<h2 id="section-9-project-time-api-routes">Section 9: Project Time: API Routes</h2>
<p>Not much on this section that I need to write down….Talks a lot about Mongo DB which I know inside out since I used it to model the data of the Survation Panel. </p>
<h2 id="section-10-working-with-app-wide-state-react-context">Section 10: Working with App-wide State (React Context)</h2>
<p>Nothing special here, it is the same as ContextProviders before…. .</p>
<h2 id="section-11-complete-app-example-build-a-full-blog-a-to-z">Section 11: Complete App Example: Build a Full Blog A to Z</h2>
<p>The only bit that’s interesting here is about converting markdown, since you could use it if you get tired of Publii, the current software I’m using for this blog you’re seeing. </p>
<h4 id="image-layout-property">Image layout property</h4>
<p>Setting the layout property of an image as “responsive” it’ll fill up the container where it is. </p>
<h4 id="translating-markdown-to-jsx">Translating MarkDown to JSX</h4>
<p>Use <a href="https://github.com/remarkjs/react-markdown">react-markdown</a>, it takes markdown and outputs it as JSX. </p>
<p>A common approach is to have a folder named “content”. You use gray matter to add metadata to markdown</p>
<p>UUse another package too called <a href="https://github.com/jonschlinkert/gray-matter">gray-matter</a></p>
<pre><code class="language-yaml">----
title: Some title
date: 2022-20-15
author: yourself
excerpt: ....
image: ....
----

And here the markdown
</code></pre>
<p>You can use <a href="https://www.udemy.com/course/nextjs-react-the-complete-guide/learn/lecture/25146246#overview">this</a> video as reference. </p>
<h4 id="getstaticprops-needs-getstaticpath">getStaticProps needs getStaticPath</h4>
<p>This is the case for all the pages that are dynamically created. </p>
<h4 id="rendering-images">Rendering images</h4>
<p>Change ReactMarkdown to render img tags as Images in NextJS with customRenderers</p>
<pre><code class="language-jsx">const customRenderers = {		
        paragraph(paragraph) {
        const { node} = paragraph
        if (node.children[0].type === &quot;image&#39;) {
        const image = node.children[0];
        return &lt;div className={classes.image}&gt;
            &lt;Image src={image.src} alt={image.alt} width={image.with} height={image.height}/&gt;
            &lt;/div&gt;
            .....
            }
            return &lt;p&gt;{paragraph.children}&lt;/p&gt;
}
</code></pre>
<h4 id="code-snippets-in-colours">Code snippets in colours</h4>
<p>Same, override the above with </p>
<p><a href="https://github.com/react-syntax-highlighter/react-syntax-highlighter">React-syntax-highlighter</a> is the package you’ll need. </p>
<h2 id="section-12-deploying-nextjs-apps">Section 12: Deploying NextJS Apps</h2>
<h4 id="next-export">Next Export</h4>
<p>It’s just a command that creates a 100% full static app and doesnt’ require a NodeJS server. But that means you cannot use API routes, server-side pages, nor page revalidations. </p>
<h4 id="nextconfigjs">next.config.js</h4>
<p>It’s better to just <a href="https://nextjs.org/docs/pages/api-reference/next-config-js">check the docs</a> for this. It has hundreds of options. </p>
<h4 id="optimising-prism-syntax-highlighter">Optimising Prism (syntax highlighter)</h4>
<p>Choose only the languages you want to import. </p>
<h2 id="section-13-adding-authentication">Section 13: Adding Authentication</h2>
<h2 id="section-14-optional-nextjs-summary">Section 14: Optional: NextJS Summary</h2>
<h2 id="section-14-course-roundup">Section 14: Course Roundup</h2>

            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Once more with feeling: Hello World!</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/once-more-with-feeling-hello-world.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/once-more-with-feeling-hello-world.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/48/vladislav-klapin-Ym6sfQFxOho-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="introductions"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:38:28+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/48/vladislav-klapin-Ym6sfQFxOho-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    Welcome to my blog, where I've consolidated all my previous WordPress and Jekyll posts into one place. My goal now is to reorganize everything and create a coherent structure. I'm transitioning from maikel.uk to maikel.dev, and this blog will reside at blog.maikel.dev. I'm Maikel, a&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/48/vladislav-klapin-Ym6sfQFxOho-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <div class="flex flex-grow flex-col gap-3">
<div class="min-h-[20px] flex items-start overflow-x-auto whitespace-pre-wrap break-words flex-col gap-4">
<div class="markdown prose w-full break-words dark:prose-invert light">
<p>Welcome to my blog, where I've consolidated all my previous WordPress and Jekyll posts into one place. My goal now is to reorganize everything and create a coherent structure.</p>
<p>I'm transitioning from maikel.uk to maikel.dev, and this blog will reside at blog.maikel.dev.</p>
<h2>So, who am I?</h2>
<p>I'm Maikel, a European-based freelance full-stack software engineer and cloud architect. My expertise lies in integrating software solutions and managing the cloud infrastructure they rely on.</p>
<p>Throughout my career, I've successfully transformed ideas from non-technical companies into reality.</p>
<p>Living currently in Seville, I'm actively seeking long-term contracts. I'm determined to demonstrate that #Mastodon and the #Fediverse can be a valuable platform for finding job opportunities or clients.</p>
<p>As a full-stack software engineer and cloud architect, my interests encompass Angular, React, Python, data science, Node.js, MongoDB, PostgreSQL, Redis, Kubernetes, Docker, Helm, Jenkins, Terraform, and Ansible. You can find more information about these topics on the homepage of this site.</p>
<p>When it comes to music, I enjoy progressive trance, lo-fi, and post-rock. As an audiophile, I have a penchant for quality audio and own Sony XM4 headphones (which I use the most), Aftershokz Titanium for running, and Senheisser 599 for optimal sound experience.</p>
<p>On a personal note, I'm gay and haven't married or had children. Although I don't have any pets of my own, I'm particularly fond of cats and have one of my flatmate at home. I identify as an atheist but maintain a tolerant attitude towards religions.</p>
<p>My hobbies include wandering and urban exploration, which means I possess an intimate knowledge of the streets in any city comparable to that of a certified taxi driver.</p>
<p>I'm here to connect with friends, clients, and potential employers.</p>
<h2>Places I've lived</h2>
<ul>
<li>London, UK</li>
<li>Manchester, UK</li>
<li>Liverpool, UK</li>
<li>Blackpool, UK</li>
<li>Cadiz, Spain</li>
<li>Barcelona, Spain</li>
<li>Seville, Spain</li>
<li>Andorra la Vella, Principality of Andorra</li>
</ul>
<p>...not in that order.</p>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Too much spare time.</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/too-much-spare-time.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/too-much-spare-time.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/22/tim-gouw-1K9T5YiZ2WU-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="diary"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:06:01+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/22/tim-gouw-1K9T5YiZ2WU-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    What can I do tomorrow Thursday? The only two things I have left are: AND if I manage to have a proper plan I either might or might not spend the weekend in Seville after the dentist. There are no available seats on the trains.
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/22/tim-gouw-1K9T5YiZ2WU-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>What can I do tomorrow Thursday? The only two things I have left are:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Appointment at 17:45 to change dressings. Where I shall ask Paloma tricks and tips to do it myself so that I could come to the surgery only once every 2 days instead of everyday.</li>
<li>Dentist on Friday at 9:45.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>AND if I manage to have a proper plan I either might or might not spend the weekend in Seville after the dentist. There are no available seats on the trains.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I could:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Read a book on kindle.</li>
<li>Watch another crappy show in Netflix. Which I'm really tired of.</li>
<li>Go for a very long walk either on my own or with friends.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Decisions, decisions.....the key thing is to burn energy.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Where do I start?</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/where-do-i-start.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/where-do-i-start.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/21/clemens-van-lay-5eThdzpVqyE-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="diary"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:04:36+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/21/clemens-van-lay-5eThdzpVqyE-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    If I were in London I would know exactly what to do and when. I'd start by checking Reed.co.uk, CW-Jobs and other jobsites to have a good grasp of what's available when doing simple searches. But by no means would I believe what I've seen&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/21/clemens-van-lay-5eThdzpVqyE-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If I were in London I would know exactly what to do and when. I'd start by checking Reed.co.uk, CW-Jobs and other jobsites to have a good grasp of what's available when doing simple searches. But by no means would I believe what I've seen there as representative of what is truly available. It's just an appetizer.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Jobsites are not even the tip of the iceberg. Most jobs are filled without them ever being posted on the internet. Someone at the company knows someone, who knows someone and is in the right place at the right time.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Being <strong>in the right place </strong>on <strong>the right time. </strong>This is what gets you the job you want. And that was my strategy in Andorra in 2007. So today I'm gathering knowledge from the past to see how can I apply it right now in El Puerto. My life is different, my skillset <strong>vastly </strong>different for starters I have one, therefore the type of job I can afford to get <strong>today </strong>is nowhere similar to the very limited options I had 15 years ago.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>My strategy in Andorra was to be <strong>ubiquitous</strong>. It wasn't hard to be honest, just need to know a vast amount of people in a tiny city and ensure they all know what you're looking for, that you're available and how to contact you. That country is tiny, so contacting the HR manager of every known company wasn't really hard, most of them are literally working in the same street (Meritxell Avenue, the only High Street of Andorra/Escaldes). Gathering the information to know who was who, maybe that was harder. Internet wasn't in 2007 what it is today. Today you can just open Linkedin to know who is in charge of hiring on every company.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>My strategy in London, couldn't be the same, because London, unlike Andorra, isn't tiny. You can only be ubiquitous in London if you're the Queen. So there my strategy was to be known by the right companies. It involved more research about where was each located, who was in charge of hiring and what they were into. London was the hardest and yet luck was a very big factor. It was a couple of key people who got me the foot on the door.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Seville was maybe, the simplest. In the UK you can't just walk into a company and say "hi, I'm hireable, here is my CV", but Andalusia is the opposite, you can literally just do that. No one would use GDPR as an excuse to avoid taking your CV, people are nosy and bored at work.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In Seville, in 2010 my approach was to locate in the map a couple of <strong>high density </strong>business centres. One was the 5 towers of Nuevo Torneo, followed by the other 6 towers nearby. The other was the 4 to 5 contiguous office buildings just after entering East Seville. I literally walked, with 20 copies of my CV made for every possible job I could imagine I was good at, generic but not too generic, I was looking for office and IT-oriented jobs, and handed it over to the hiring manager on every office. If he or she wasn't there I didn't waste paper. I put emphasis on the 20 copies because it is probably no more than it took me to start working for Clearwire.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Hiring is a game of putting yourself in the shoes of the hiring manager. From their perspective, you're being <strong>auctioned</strong>. They know you're hireable for a <strong>very</strong> limited time, once you find a job you're out of the market. Their opportunity is lost, your talent is elsewhere.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In the UK being ubiquitous requires an online presence. Emails back and forth to the right people at the right companies. Too much networking.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>El Puerto is, weird. It's a strange city that I can't place nor compare to any of the other places I've been. It has an industry but I can't figure the size of it, it is <strong>not </strong>only dedicated to tourism, even though that's the appearance it kind of gives.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>One of the companies that has eScooters for hire is based in this city, I can't figure out why when they don't even offer that service here. They were only operating in Seville and Cádiz (the capital city, not the province). More and more companies are taking up space in the Salinas business area nearby my home. I wonder how cheap or convenient is the square metre there. In a nutshell, El Puerto has the appearance of non-tourism orientated <strong>growth </strong>and if I can, for once, be part of that I would love to.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I run away from this city in 2007, never looked back, gave it for lost, accepted all jobs that could be taken in this city were in the waitressing industry. But now, so many years later, I have the strong feeling that has changed and this city may be becoming the economic engine of the Bay. Which sounds exciting because it means I might be able to settle down back in my hometown.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Sure, London is exciting, travelling wherever, living in Barcelona, or having the right to work in Andorra (which isn't easy at all) makes you feel special but....I never wanted special. I want, <strong>home</strong>. The place where my body is accustomed to its weather, the place where the food is what I've grown up eating, the place where family and most friends are. The place I want to have <strong>a mortgage</strong> in.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>So here I am, this is what I had:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Remote working 24/7</li>
<li>My own schedule organised by me.</li>
<li>I could choose what tech to use for each page, service, website. Including what programming language and framework.</li>
<li>A salary that allowed me to not worry about money.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This is what I offer now:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Don't care about remote or going to an office. Unless the office has air conditioning in which case I prefer it.</li>
<li>Knowledge of Python, JavaScript, back-end &amp; front-end frameworks. Self-directed learning whenever I need some extra knowledge on anything.</li>
<li>An upper second-class honours degree on Computing and IT by the Open University.</li>
<li>A brain that never stops.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This is what I want now:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Permanency. I don't want more project work, more fixed date work. I want my new job to be my last job. The one I'll do all the way to my retirement.</li>
<li>In the Cadiz Bay.</li>
<li>I want an amount of fixed hours per week. No more 24/7 monitoring of website A, B, C running smoothly and having to be no more than 1km away from my laptop to fix anything at 3am looking at Nagios/Sensu.</li>
<li>Clear definition of my duties. I don't want to run ever again an entire software engineering department. It's bad for my skillset.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Client seeking in the Scientific and Technologic Complex of Cartuja</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/client-seeking-in-the-scientific-and-technologic-complex-of-cartuja.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/client-seeking-in-the-scientific-and-technologic-complex-of-cartuja.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/43/pablo-manuel-santos-breval-jKT5qKKrgiQ-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="jobhunting"/>
            <category term="diary"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:25:48+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/43/pablo-manuel-santos-breval-jKT5qKKrgiQ-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    I'm looking for clients in the PCT (Scientific and Techno Park in Spanish) Cartuja and I'm going to describe here what I'm doing exactly for future reference. This could work as a model of what to do in the future, in other places, based in&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/43/pablo-manuel-santos-breval-jKT5qKKrgiQ-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I'm looking for clients in the PCT (Scientific and Techno Park in Spanish) Cartuja and I'm going to describe here what I'm doing exactly for future reference. This could work as a model of what to do in the future, in other places, based in the <a href="https://www.digitalocean.com/community/tutorials/what-is-dry-development">DRY </a>principle of software engineering.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The first thing I did to make it a bit fun was to have a very long, ride around every street in the area to get a good grasp of the buildings, the locations, the names of the streets, browsing where the main divisions are. I've noticed in some bits it's all medical, other bits of the place are taken by the University of Seville's campus. Not all of the Cartuja island is useful to me then. It seems all that could matter is <strong>in the middle section</strong>.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I shall not forget about the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Estadio_de_La_Cartuja">Stadium</a>, because apart from sport events it has also offices. Even though Wikipedia makes no mention of it. In any case it has its own <a href="https://www.estadiolacartuja.es/">website</a>. I know there's a company called Inn Offices that rents spaces in the Stadium but they don't seem to have a directory of companies and start ups running <strong>with </strong>them. I know their website is <a href="https://innoffices.es/alquiler-de-oficinas/">this</a>.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>On the website of the PCT there is a section of jobs <a href="https://www.pctcartuja.es/es/ofertas-de-empleo.html">here</a> but I'm not very keen on it as I'm not eager to become anyone's employee. I rather stay independent unless it's strictly necessary to change that or someone makes a really enticing offer.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Today I'm doing just a bit of discovery and gathering tasks to do at the end of this post.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The directory of companies is <a href="https://www.pctcartuja.es/es/established-companies-pctcartuja.html">here</a> and it seems they are exactly 493. I shouldn't assume that directory is updated.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>The goal</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>To be re-employed ASAP.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>How to measure it?</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>In time and steps, the number of steps it takes me to get clients and the number of days. The reason to measure it is so that I can compare in the future, methods of client of client gathering. Today is day zero. To gather the number of steps I should work backwards from what works, using these posts as reference.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>To do:</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Check the <a href="https://www.estadiolacartuja.es/">website</a> of the stadium.</li>
<li>Read the <a href="https://www.pctcartuja.es/es/ofertas-de-empleo.html">vacancies</a> website of the PCT.</li>
<li>Everyone around me should know I'm open to opportunities. <strong>Make them </strong>aware.</li>
<li>Read the website of the <a href="https://www.pctcartuja.es/es">PCT</a> itself. Find what's useful there.</li>
<li>Use Scrapy to download the entire directory. Or just copy and paste the tables, actually.</li>
<li>Publish this post.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Distractions:</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Starbucks as a location to do some work is a double-edged sword. On one side, the air con makes it nice, when it'll be <strong>absolutely bloody awful</strong> elsewhere, and the constant movement of people keeps me somehow focused. On the other side the feeling of needing to purchase something every hour (not that anyone asks me to do so) makes me never stay here more than 1 hour. What I need is a place where I can stay for at least four hours then continue from home.</li>
<li>Friends bothering me through WhatsApp. Maybe I should tell them from X to Y time I'm busy.</li>
<li>Had to get an evaporative air cooler. Considering Seville is extra dry, it is the perfect city to use this kind of coolers and save a ton of money in air conditioning.</li>
<li>This site isn't working on mobile, the menu button doesn't do anything. Fix the upper left button. Otherwise this blog is unnacesible from the home page.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Decisions time</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/decisions-time.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/decisions-time.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/20/jon-tyson-PXB7yEM5LVs-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="diary"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:03:24+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/20/jon-tyson-PXB7yEM5LVs-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    This post is going to run for a while. I've invested the last couple of weeks in quitting caffeine. I've been caffeine free for 2 weeks, right now I'm heading back to it. Dullness. Life becomes meaningless without it. It's not an state of depression&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/20/jon-tyson-PXB7yEM5LVs-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This post is going to run for a while. I've invested the last couple of weeks in quitting caffeine. I've been caffeine free for 2 weeks, right now I'm heading back to it.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Why am I going back to coffee?</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Dullness. Life becomes meaningless without it. It's not an state of depression after the 3rd day but a state of carelessness. It is literally the opposite from caring too much about everything to not caring at all. What I want is balance and to get balance I'm going to need coffee. So what I need to mind about is the tolerance to it.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I'm going to drink just enough to have a meaningful workout and sleep whenever needed. So if that coffee makes me sleepy, I'm sleeping. Same as my calories are distributed throughout the day I'm going to let the sleeping hours do the same.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Rethinking the gym routine.</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I haven't gone to the gym either, the lack of care for life of quitting coffee had made going to the gym a shore. Which is another of the reasons I'm going back or specifically going back to coffee pre-workout <strong>only. </strong></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I've tried to no avail for 2 weeks to rotate my sleeping pattern to wake up at 4:30am and I simply can't without the aid of coffee. Even the sleeping pills (Dormidina) only help me sleep a couple of hours during the day when I try to sleep early. So I haven't gone at all to the gym.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I'm quit maintenance now and head for heavy fat loss.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><strong>UPDATE: </strong>So I've gone to the gym after having 1 coffee and it cost me nothing, it's really MUCH more pleasurable to go caffeinated than decaf. I also remade my workout routine (pec/back everyday except when legs in a configuration of day 1, day legs, day 2, day legs) so I train every major muscle (pec &amp; back) more often.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>This blog</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I should stick to one post until that post is completed. If there are multiple subjects within that post I should chunk them only when writing in that post is over once it becomes too big.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Where am I living?</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This is one of the most annoying subjects because it is heavily interconnected to other subjects. Facts:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Where I live might dictate where I can work, unless I count remote. That is, I could find a remote work and stay wherever I actually want.</li>
<li>The sensible thing would be to stay nearby for as long as the armpit surgery is done.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Health stuff and location</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3>Teeth</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This week's 8th of April (Friday) I'm getting, in theory, the aligners put back on. That means freedom to move around for 3 months from that date. So in theory until July I can be wherever. In reality this become a non-issue if I simply get a job within Cadiz province. In an ideal scenario I'd like to stay in Spain until my teeth treatment is fully done.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading {"level":3} --></p>
<h3>Armpits</h3>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I'm in waiting list. In theory I'm there for up to six months. The doctor said they usually perform it within 3 months. But online news says on average Puerta del Mar (the hospital) has a 160 days waiting list. That means it can take until October for me to get the surgery.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Technically I could move wherever as far as it's somewhere that allows me to come back. The problem is not what I do while I'm out. The problem is once I get the surgery I might not be able to do anything (I'd be temporarily incapacitated) for a few weeks.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Location</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>So where am I moving in May is the main question that this post intends to answer. The price of anything for May in AirBnB negates not working, meaning it is entirely unaffordable without a job. If I stay in Cádiz I would need to pull out a favour. What I would like:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list {"ordered":true} --></p>
<ol>
<li>A good gym where I can train without it being at ridiculous AM.</li>
<li>Green areas to walk around, pine forest or just forests.</li>
</ol>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>So this table is the 3 options that come to mind right now but I'm not limited to them.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:table {"className":"is-style-stripes"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-table is-style-stripes">
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th> </th>
<th>Cadiz Province</th>
<th>Madrid</th>
<th>London</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Pros</td>
<td>* Dentist and armpit surgery location troubles solved. <br>* Most friends are here. <br>* Luismi is here<br>* Known gyms<br>* Good only if lucky and found cheap accommodation. <br>* I don't have to move all my stuff. <br>* If Chiclana, San Fernando or El Puerto then it's more interesting. <br>* The most sensible counting with the time you're going to be temporarily incapacitated post surgery.</td>
<td>* More affordable in summer.<br>* Big city. <br>* New city, exciting. <br>* Puts me closer to home ownership as I might get a job within Spain. <br>* Surely has more than one good gym. <br>* Easier to get a bigger salary. <br>* Might help me delink my career from the UK.</td>
<td>* Some friends might let me stay at theirs until I find long-term options. <br>* Many friends in London<br>* Renewal of the 5 years of the indefinite leave to remain. <br>* Might be the easiest to get highest possible income. <br>* Good gyms everywhere. <br>* Places to run everywhere. <br>* Cooler in summer.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>Cons</td>
<td>* Unaffordable in summer.<br>* Hot in summer. <br>* Sameness, boring, dull if the capital. <br>* Finding a job is harder. You have to basically relay only on remote working as salaries on the province are laughable on anything. <br>* There's no IT industry.</td>
<td>* Got to travel to get to dentist/surgery.<br>* Have to move all my stuff or keep it in my aunts place.</td>
<td>* Got to take a plane to get to dentist/surgery.<br>* Sameness. <br>* Can't use the eScooter. <br>* Can't take most of my stuff.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<figcaption>Where to stay</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><!-- /wp:table --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Routine attempt 1</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/routine-attempt-1.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/routine-attempt-1.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/42/mahdis-mousavi-Oj3BAOj5pTk-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="workingout"/>
            <category term="dieting"/>
            <category term="diary"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:24:16+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/42/mahdis-mousavi-Oj3BAOj5pTk-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    You could have your meals at a fix hour. No coffee. 4 meals, maybe 6am, 10am, 2pm, 6pm. That's 1 every 4 hours and a 12 hours fast. 30 grams of protein on each meal. Every meal should have greens or at least lettuce. What's&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/42/mahdis-mousavi-Oj3BAOj5pTk-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li><strong>4:30 am</strong>: Wake up, go to the gym, run there and shower.</li>
<li><strong>6:00 am: </strong>Go back home, eat something. After-workout meal.</li>
<li><strong>10:00 am: </strong>Breakfast.</li>
<li><strong>2:00 pm: </strong>Lunch</li>
<li><strong>6:00 pm: </strong>Dinner.</li>
<li><strong>8pm: </strong>Go to sleep.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Notes</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>You could have your meals at a fix hour. <br>No coffee. <br>4 meals, maybe 6am, 10am, 2pm, 6pm. That's 1 every 4 hours and a 12 hours fast. <br>30 grams of protein on each meal. <br>Every meal should have greens or at least lettuce. <br>What's the goal? To slowly drift into 14% body fat <strong>without </strong>losing muscle (body recomp). We know it works by knowing the weight you lift remains the same as today 17/03/2022 in workit.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I need to go out.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>New health goals</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I don't want more muscle, I want less fat. Keeping the muscle is a priority while losing the fat. You need goals, changes in routine that are sustainable and traceable for progression:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list {"ordered":true} --></p>
<ol>
<li>Try a 3 times per week weigh lifting and see if you can still lift the same after 3 weeks.</li>
<li>You shouldn't track weight, when you do you go too quick. You can glance at it.</li>
<li>You shouldn't track body fat even though 14% is the goal.</li>
<li>Track the exercise you do. HIIT and LISS to be specific. Specially LISS.</li>
<li>Your goal every day is to go to sleep exhausted. So the opposite of what you're currently doing.</li>
<li>Calories is all that you should track.</li>
</ol>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Real questions</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>How do I add cardio when there's nowhere likeable to run in Cádiz?</li>
<li>Can I increase my BMR (basal metabolic rate) ?</li>
<li>Once you get the key you can put the scooter on the storage room.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2>Basic Meal Plan</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>At 2359 calories total it should be divided in:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Carbs: 295 grams</li>
<li>Fat: 79 grams</li>
<li>Protein: 118 grams</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That's per meal of 74 carbs, 20 fat, 30 protein when spread in 4 meals.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:table --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-table">
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Time</td>
<td>Food</td>
<td>Macros</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6am</td>
<td>Protein Oat Bran +1 green apple</td>
<td>61C, 8F, 46P</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>10am</td>
<td>3 pears + 50 grams edamame</td>
<td>91C, 8F, 21P</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>2pm</td>
<td>Chicken breast salad with tomato and olive oil</td>
<td>4G, 30G, 34G</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td>6pm</td>
<td>150 grams of muesli, 2 green apples</td>
<td>119G, 20G, 14G.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<figcaption>Basic Meal Plan</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><!-- /wp:table --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This basic meal plan has almost the 2359 calories, it falls short by 200 calories.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Learning CMS</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/learning-cms.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/learning-cms.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/14/visitor.png" medium="image" />
            <category term="portfolio"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:00:03+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/14/visitor.png" alt="" />
                    This is a personal project of a learning platform. I wanted to facilitate the acquisition of skills by controlling the status of each one of them, knowing where to update them, which ones do I already know, etc. While having an interface to write notes&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/14/visitor.png" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This is a personal project of a learning platform. I wanted to facilitate the acquisition of skills by controlling the status of each one of them, knowing where to update them, which ones do I already know, etc. While having an interface to write notes about them and test my own knowledge. As a result I built my own self-directed learning CMS on Angular 4, Node, Express and MongoDB on an Amazon EC3 Ubuntu container.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The website is fully responsive, so it adapts to mobile phones when opened from them. You're free to access the source code in github.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>On a caffeine high</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/on-a-caffeine-high.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/on-a-caffeine-high.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/12/anastasia-zhenina-PMnJWQ1F_ww-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="diary"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T15:49:20+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/12/anastasia-zhenina-PMnJWQ1F_ww-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    I had an awful week, really bloody awful week. We start it by realising I've been waiting 2 months for the Invisalign aligners to arrive when they were never going to do so. The appointment I had for the 27th of January wasn't to get&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/12/anastasia-zhenina-PMnJWQ1F_ww-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="an-awful-week">An awful week</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I had an awful week, really bloody awful week. We start it by realising I've been waiting 2 months for the Invisalign aligners to arrive when they were never going to do so. The appointment I had for the 27th of January wasn't to get them put back on, I was lied. That appointment was to get the measurements and reorder them. Not only that I was again lied on that occasion.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This wouldn't matter much shall I have not paid in advance for my whole treatment and I was imprisoned with my current clinic. So I ended up moving the treatment to another one, closer, I no longer have to commute to Seville to see my dentist now I have it here. But I'm still wasting time in a limbo until they send them my whole dental history. This is half a victory. On a good note, the new dentist believes he won't need to take two of my healthy teeth out to make space.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>This whole money situation made me really nervous, I knew it is either now I fix my teeth or not in the foreseeable future. So it made me really anxious. But to be fair, I'm glad I have my dentist nearby now.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="freedom-awaits">Freedom awaits</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Shortly I'd be able to redirect all my working efforts to do what I please, which is to learn as much as possible in the shortest span of time possible, at all times.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>That also means I will be able to pursue other streams of income and this is what has me wondering the most about the future.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But I want routine. I've come to the realisation that there's nothing I love more than routine. Going to the gym has made me aware of this more than ever. I get a baseline that works, then I work on that baseline. Something that others might deem boring I find creative. I evolve the routine from "working" to "being the most efficient". With the gym, I have no doubts the way I'm doing it is the most efficient <strong>right now</strong>. And yet there's plenty of room for improvement, it is that room for improvement what keeps me entertained. And it is the fact that this can all be applied to all other matters of life, especially work, what has me looking forward to be able to think for 3 months in just, this.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Regarding new streams of income some ideas come to mind:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>I should write mobile apps non-stop, get better at failing with them just to learn to write them quickly.</li>
<li>I'm never going to be financially independent unless I work for no one. Working for others will never give me job stability.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Now I wonder what I'd like to do, whether to start straight-away looking for that source of income or have relaxed holidays. I honestly don't think I'm capable of the latter, for the very same reason I said above, I'm a routine-junkie, I love routine, I love structure.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>But as my favourite quote says:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:quote --></p>
<blockquote class="wp-block-quote">
<p>Process saves us from the poverty of our intentions.</p>
<p><cite>by Elizabeth King</cite></p>
</blockquote>
<p><!-- /wp:quote --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>So I want to have a timeline or what I'm doing. My last day for them is the 20th of February so roughly in 20 days. I'm basically picking up from where I left on January 2019 when I started this solopreneur odyssey. I just want to polish the edges of what hasn't worked so far and carry on with what worked fine.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>My goal is pretty simple, I want to make enough money to not have to worry about the stability of it while at the same time do something rewarding for it. The quickest path to reward is doing whatever increases my skillset, doing that makes me happy. But the problem I've seen with the last 3 years is I never demanded a payrise to go with it.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I want to buy a house, I could have done that on my current salary yet the instability of it is what prevented me from even trying. In other words: <strong>I put all my eggs on the same unreliable basket. </strong></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>And the funny thing is I didn't have to, my skillset is rock solid, it was my client who wasn't.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>One of the main things I want to do is avoid entirely having to go to London.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:heading --></p>
<h2 id="back-to-my-routine">Back to my routine.</h2>
<p><!-- /wp:heading --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The centre of my routine is going to be, as it is now: <strong>health. </strong>I've come to realise when I put that as the top-most priority I'm at my happiest.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>If I didn't have to go find another job I'll even get a comprehensive health insurance.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>So my new routine has to include:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>Health stuff
<ul>
<li>Doing HIIT. Preferably in the morning.</li>
<li>Getting to 13% body fat.</li>
<li>Eating healthier.</li>
<li>Mind stuff: going out, exploring, preferably with other people.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Work stuff
<ul>
<li>Invest in skillset</li>
<li>Putting it to practice, actually earning money.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Crash diet</title>
        <author>
            <name>Maikel</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://blog.maikel.dev/crash-diet.html"/>
        <id>https://blog.maikel.dev/crash-diet.html</id>
        <media:content url="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/thought-catalog-fnztlIb52gU-unsplash.jpg" medium="image" />
            <category term="dieting"/>
            <category term="diary"/>

        <updated>2023-06-26T16:22:44+02:00</updated>
            <summary>
                <![CDATA[
                        <img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/thought-catalog-fnztlIb52gU-unsplash.jpg" alt="" />
                    I've been feeling bloated this week. I was on a bulking cycle and that's normal yet to a point. I started to dislike my image on the mirror, especially around my neck which was getting chubby again very quickly. So I started this crash diet&hellip;
                ]]>
            </summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <p><img src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/thought-catalog-fnztlIb52gU-unsplash.jpg" class="type:primaryImage" alt="" /></p>
                <p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I've been feeling bloated this week. I was on a bulking cycle and that's normal yet to a point. I started to dislike my image on the mirror, especially around my neck which was getting chubby again very quickly.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>So I started this crash diet on the middle of Wednesday the 19th after Luismi left. The idea was pretty basic:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>20-minute HIIT in intervals of 1-minute at 5 kmph then 1-minute at 11 kmph.</li>
<li>Weightlifting on series of 3 per exercise as usual when cutting.</li>
<li>Intermittent "broken" DRY fasting from around 5 or 6pm onwards 16 hours minimum.</li>
<li>LISS everyday. Just getting out and waking around for an hour or longer.</li>
<li>1 pill of Synephrine with 1 vial of L-Carnitine immediately before heading to the gym.</li>
<li>Measure caloric consumption with MyFitnessPal.</li>
<li>Break the dry part of the fasting after the gym with just 1 coffee with no milk, so you're still fasting because coffee has no calories.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>The results:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>I'm ignoring body fat and muscle mass as both are wildly inconsistent, instead let's focus on accurate targets:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":457,"sizeSlug":"large"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-457"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/image_editor_output_image-933024081-1642817107956.jpg" alt="" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/image_editor_output_image-933024081-1642817107956-xs.jpg 300w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/image_editor_output_image-933024081-1642817107956-sm.jpg 480w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/image_editor_output_image-933024081-1642817107956-md.jpg 768w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/image_editor_output_image-933024081-1642817107956-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/image_editor_output_image-933024081-1642817107956-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/image_editor_output_image-933024081-1642817107956-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure>
<figcaption>Trend of my weight over 3 days</figcaption>
</figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>My weight has lowered by quite a lot and I feel far less bloated. I didn't stop having protein nor creatine.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Things I noticed:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list {"ordered":true} --></p>
<ol>
<li>The first day this is incredibly easy to do. The second day is easy. The third day was when it started to get hard.</li>
<li>As usual during a fast I get over energised by it.</li>
<li>For first time in a long time I can run and not any run. I could run at a pace of 11 kms per hour which is not the leisure pace I'm accustomed to.</li>
</ol>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:image {"id":462,"sizeSlug":"large"} --></p>
<figure class="wp-block-image size-large"><figure class="wp-image-462"><img loading="lazy"  src="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/Screenshot_20220122_032149.jpg" alt="" sizes="(max-width: 48em) 100vw, 768px" srcset="https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/Screenshot_20220122_032149-xs.jpg 300w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/Screenshot_20220122_032149-sm.jpg 480w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/Screenshot_20220122_032149-md.jpg 768w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/Screenshot_20220122_032149-lg.jpg 1024w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/Screenshot_20220122_032149-xl.jpg 1360w ,https://blog.maikel.dev/media/posts/40/responsive/Screenshot_20220122_032149-2xl.jpg 1600w"></figure></figure>
<p><!-- /wp:image --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list {"ordered":true,"start":4} --></p>
<ol start="4">
<li>The fact my gym treadmill has the game solitaire makes the running time fly effortlessly. While at 5 I play normal, while at 11 I just look at all possible movements. It's exactly as above.</li>
<li>The weightlifting in a fasted state does not bother my performance in the slightest.</li>
<li>On the third day it becomes impossible to continue. That was the day I dropped HIIT, I simply couldn't do it.</li>
<li>I could feel on the third day I couldn't go any heavier nor train at my strongest, unlike the previous too.</li>
<li>It could be caused by having had the fast started wayyy too early this third day at around 2pm instead of 6pm. I should have kept it consistent. But I woke up early (I wake up usually past noon) because I had a package of protein delivered and the driver woke me up when he pressed the doorbell.</li>
<li>I still feel, even considering the previous one, that I hit the max low I can go doing this.</li>
<li>The novelty of this crash diet is I got around 100 grams or more of protein every day during my feeding period. Other times I've done it I just ate anything in low amounts without paying much attention to macros.</li>
<li>I've eaten roughly 1200 calories only per day during this period.</li>
<li>All I'm losing is obviously water and if I were back on a bulk I would just regain it just as quick. I need to find a middle path.</li>
<li>The third day unsurprisingly, only 100 grams were lost in the gym. When I do HIIT I literally lose a kilogram. I know it's just water but water matters.</li>
</ol>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>During the day I took several measurements, the top of each curve is always just before I start each fasting period, so at my heaviest. The bottom is the <strong>official </strong>weight, the consistent one I get when I wake up. Therefore I started 3 days ago with 73.1kgs and tomorrow morning predictably I'll be around 3 kgs lighter.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Now the other accurate measure is waist circumference. That is now FILL THIS UP.</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:paragraph --></p>
<p>Some conclusions:</p>
<p><!-- /wp:paragraph --></p>
<p><!-- wp:list --></p>
<ul>
<li>I need to prevent water retention.</li>
<li>One of the ways I can control water consumption is by looking at my weight. Chosing a figure I can't go above despite cycling bulking/cutting.</li>
<li>That figure could be 70 kgs because anything above that and I start looking bloated.</li>
<li>Limiting the amount of protein shakes taken per day can also help with water retention. I can do this by getting more daily doses protein from meat and fish instead of liquid forms.</li>
<li>Strangely the more water I drink, the less I seem to flush out.</li>
<li>Consuming creatine or not makes no difference to water retention. While not consuming it, shortly starts to affect my performance when weightlifting.</li>
<li>This diet is not feasible for longer periods than 3 days.</li>
</ul>
<p><!-- /wp:list --></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
